Lowell Thomas Jr. Papers
Marist College Archives and Special Collections
Lowell Thomas Jr. Papers
1938-2014
Lowell Thomas Jr. (1923-2016)
90.5 Linear feet 40 Boxes 379 Folders
Lowell Thomas Jr. was born on 6 October 1923 in London, England, to Lowell Jackson Thomas (1892-1981) and Frances Ryan Thomas (1893-1975). His early childhood was spent in New York City and would spend weekends at the family home in Quaker Hill. In 1949, he and his father, Lowell Thomas Sr. became two of the few Westerners allowed entry into Tibet. In 1958, he and his wife, Mary “Tay” Pryor flew to Alaska with their toddler Anne and fell in love with the territory where they would remain residents for the rest of their lives. Soon after moving to Anchorage, Lowell Thomas Jr. began his many years of public service. Lowell Thomas Jr. devoted much of his time and money to conservation issues and public service, and he and Tay aided many charitable causes. This collection consists of materials created or saved by Lowell Thomas Jr. including various documents and memorabilia. Materials on his political career include newspaper clippings correspondences, and a book. This collection also contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, and notes on Lowell Thomas Jr.’s environmental involvement, personal life, as well as materials on his travels to Tibet, Turkey, and Persia.
Marist College Archives and Special Collections James A. Cannavino Library, First Floor, Room 134 3399 North Road Poughkeepsie New York 12601 United States
There are no restrictions on this collection
Lowell Thomas Jr. was born on 6 October 1923 in London, England, to Lowell Jackson Thomas (1892-1981) and Frances Ryan Thomas (1893-1975). His early childhood was spent in New York City due to his father’s work broadcasting a nightly radio news show. He and his parents would spend weekends at the family home in Quaker Hill.
After graduating from Taft School in 1942, Lowell Thomas Jr. went to Dartmouth College before his studies were interrupted by World War II and he enlisted in the United States Army Air Corps. Before he could see combat, he suffered from an illness and, instead, became a flight instructor during the war. Following the war, he returned to Dartmouth and graduated in the class of 1946. Lowell Thomas Jr. developed passions for flying and skiing that he would continue for the rest of his life. After graduation, he traveled to Iran and Turkey, where he collected materials for travelogues that he presented on a U.S. tour during the winter of 1948-49.
In 1949, he and his father, Lowell Thomas Sr., the renowned broadcaster, writer, and world traveler became two of the few Westerners allowed entry into Tibet. The responsibility for filming, photographing, and tape recording the sights and sounds of Tibetan life fell mostly to Lowell Thomas Jr. During the journey back out of Tibet, his father was thrown from his horse shattering his hip. The rough, narrow roads to and from Tibet would not allow the passage of automobiles and with little medical supplies, Lowell Thomas Jr. created a makeshift stretcher for his father. Lowell Thomas Jr. wrote the bestselling book, Out of This World, and later produced a documentary of the same name. In 2005, the Dalai Lama referred to him as “one of the genuine grandfathers of the Tibet movement in America” and bestowed upon him the International Campaign for Tibet’s Light of Truth Award.
Following his return from Tibet, Lowell Thomas Jr. married Mary “Tay” Pryor. They were married for 64 years until her death in 2014. In 1954, he and Tay bought a Cessna 180 in which they traveled much of the globe while documenting their travels. They would publish articles on their trip and co-wrote the book, Our Flight to Adventure.
In 1958, they flew to Alaska with their toddler Anne and fell in love with the territory. Two years later, they would relocate there and would remain residents of Alaska for the rest of their lives.
Soon after moving to Anchorage, Lowell Thomas Jr. began his many years of public service. After unsuccessfully running twice for the U.S. House, he ran for state Senate. From 1967 to 1974, Lowell Thomas Jr. represented the Alaska Senate from District E as a Republican.
Thomas also became deeply involved in conservation issues. Some of his notable contributions were his work against the bounty hunting of wolves and work that led to the establishment of Chugach State Park in 1970.
In 1974, Lowell Thomas Jr. was elected as Alaska’s third lieutenant governor under Governor Jay Hammond. However, a controversy arose after remarks Thomas made were interpreted as approving of apartheid in South Africa. Hammond backed Thomas, calling it a hypocritical smear, but accepted his decision not to seek a second term.
Following his time in office, Lowell Thomas Jr. bought Talkeetna Air Taxi Service in 1981, an Alaskan bush pilot service, and remained an active pilot into his 80s. He shuttled skiers in the Alaska Range and onto North America’s tallest peak, Denali in his Helio Courier. Lowell Thomas Jr. has logged over 10,000 hours in the air without ever scratching a plane. In 2012, Lowell Thomas Jr. was inducted into the Aviation Museum Hall of Fame to which he also donated his beloved Helio Courier.
Lowell Thomas Jr. devoted much of his time and money to conservation issues and public service, and he and Tay aided many charitable causes. Among the many organizations the Thomases supported were the Alaska Conservation Foundation, the National Parks, and the Conservation Association. He helped to create the Thomas Planetarium at the Anchorage Museum, the Thomas Training Center on Eagle Glacier near Girdwood, and the Thomas Center for Senior Living at St. Mary’s Episcopal Church. Lowell Thomas Jr. was awarded a lifetime achievement award by the National Parks Conservation Association in 1995 and awarded the William Penn Mott Jr. Leadership Award by the Alaska Conservation Foundation in 2004. In 2011, the Alaska Conservation Foundation established the Lowell Thomas, Jr. Award for outstanding achievement by an Alaskan-based organization or program.
Lowell Thomas Jr. wrote several books, including Out of This World: Across the Himalayas to Forbidden Tibet, The Silent War in Tibet, and Our Flight to Adventure.
On 1 October 2016, Lowell Thomas Jr., aged 92, died.
This collection consists of materials created or saved by Lowell Thomas Jr. including various documents and memorabilia. Materials on his political career include newspaper clippings correspondences, and a book. This collection also contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, and notes on Lowell Thomas Jr.’s environmental involvement, personal life, as well as materials on his travels to Tibet, Turkey, and Persia. There are many objects in this collection including serval cameras and film materials, clothes, and achievements. This collection also contains numerous photographs, including photographs of Lowell Thomas Sr. and personal photographs of Lowell Thomas Jr. and friends.
Thomas, Lowell, 1923-2016; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981; Skis and skiing--History; Trans-Alaska Pipeline (Alaska); Cessna 180 (Private plane); Alaska; Tibet Region
This collection is organized into eight series: 1) Political, 2) Conservation issues and public service, 3) Personal, 4) Tibet, 5) Turkey and Persia, 6) Objects, 7) Photographs and Film Negatives, and 8) Miscellany.
The collection was donated to Marist College Archives & Special Collections by the Thomas family.
No accruals are expected.
Lowell Thomas Film Collection
Lowell Thomas Memorabilia Collection
Lowell Thomas Papers: Graphic Materials
Lowell Thomas Papers: Objects
Lowell Thomas Papers: Textual Materials
- 1. Political, 1962-1979
  Series contains newspaper clippings and a book related to Lowell Thomas Jr.’s political career from unsuccessful runs for the U.S. House before winning a seat in the Senate and serving as Lieutenant Governor under Governor Jay Hammond. This series contains photocopies of newspaper clippings.
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Manual of Legislative Procedure for Legislative and Other Governmental Bodies and Alaska Statutes, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Congressional Record-Senate, September 1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Do You Know Your Economic ABC's?, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1964 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Mirror of Opinion Deed Before Words, June 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Campaign Bulletin #1 and Campaign Bulletin #2, August 1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Sample General Election Ballot, November 1964 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - State of New York Message to the Legislature and Newspaper Clippings, January 1965 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, February 1965 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Realities of Vietnam by Rajmohan Gandi, April 1965 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - The Ripon Forum, May 1965 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Lowell Thomas Jr. Eyes Political Posts In Alaska, January 1966 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1966 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1966 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1968 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1968 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1968 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1968 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1968 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1968 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Jr. to William Babcock, April 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Longest-Most Frustrating Legislative Session-Summarized and The Sales Executive Magazine, May 1969 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1969 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1970 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Here Are the Latest Results In the District 8 House Race, September 1970 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1970 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1970 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1972 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1972 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1972 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Injury Control, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1973 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Hickel and Stevens State Oil Views, February 1974 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1974 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Hammond Seeks Win With Wit, Wisdom, May 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1974 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Official filings for office listed, July 1974 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1974 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Times Action Unfair, September 1974 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1974 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Biographical Sketch, December 1974 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1975 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Hammond's New Job Has Its Ups, Downs, December 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1977 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Correspondences, November 1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1977 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - The National Conference of Lieutenant Governors and Free-For-All Newspaper Clipping, March 1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1978 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Session passes '77 in length, May 1978 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1978 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1978 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1978 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1978 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1978 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1978 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1979 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Election Suit Cost The State $292,000, May 1979 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Election reforms proposed, September 1979 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 4, Folder 25)
- 2. Conservation issues and public service, 1960-1984; 148 folders
  Series contains newspaper clippings on various conservation issues and public service including the Trans-Alaska Pipeline, Alaska’s land, pollution, the “d-2” provision, and abortion laws. This series contains photocopies of newspaper clippings.
  - From forests of Alaska...To rayon mills of Japan, June 1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - The Bee-Hive, September 1960 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - The Anchorage Schools 1961-1962 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Alaska's Marvelous Monster-The King Crab, March 1962 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1962 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1962 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Here's What Happened In Kodiak When Katmai Erupted Fifty Years Ago, June 1962 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1962 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Look Toward 'Days of 1967' in Alaska, September 1962 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1962 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1962 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1962 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Malaspina in Alaska, January 1963 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Fort Reconstruction Plan At Kenai Needs Community Support, Educator Warns, February 1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Alyeska Report, March 1963 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1963 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1963 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Alaska Development Digest, December 1963 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1964 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Ketchikan Seeking Ferries Promotion, July 1964 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Massive Program to Provide Education, Training, Jobs; Much Application in State, August 1964 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Magazines and Newspaper Clippings, September 1964 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1964 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Anchorage Daily Times (November 5, 1964), November 1964 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1964 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Facts Digest 1964-1965 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1965 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1965 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1965 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Washington: Farewell to Brother Ed, April 1965 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Alaskans In Paradise, May 1965 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Clippings, June 1965 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1965 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1965 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1965 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1966 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Review of Business and Economic Conditions (September 1966) (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Review of Business and Economic Conditions (November 1966) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Growing Pains in Anchorage Borough Schools, 1966 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1967 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Scholastic Teacher, Nancy Lake Plan Budget Program, and The Explorers Club Explorers Journal, March 1967 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Review of Business and Economic Conditions (April 1966), April 1967 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - What Others Say From One Oil State To Another and Alaska Construction and Oil Report (May 1967) (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Alaska Sportsman (June 1967) and Alaska Construction and Oil Report (June 1967) (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - National Estuarine Pollution Study, July 1967 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1967 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Alaska Sportsman (November 1967) (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1967 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - A Progress Reports to the Commissioner of Indian Affairs, The Wien Brother's Story, Discover Alaska First At Cordova, and The Seal of the State of Alaska Inaugural Program 1967 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Alaska Sportsman (January 1968), Journal of the Hydraulics Division Proceedings of the American Society of Civil Engineers (January1968), and Newspaper Clippings (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Correspondence, February 1968 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Canadian Geographical Journal (March 1968) and Newspaper Clippings (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Drug Abuse: Escape to Nowhere and Newspaper Clippings, April 1968 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - State Government News (May 1968) and Newspaper Clippings (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - State Government (Summer, 1968) and Newspaper Clippings, June 1968 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Alaska Sportsman (July 1968) and Newspaper Clippings (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1968 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1968 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1968 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1969 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1969 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1969 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1969 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1969 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1969 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - A Plea for Understanding of Mental Health, July 1969 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1969 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1969 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1969 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1969 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Economic Considerations Relevant to Severance Taxation of Alaskan Oil and Gas (1970) and Newspaper Clippings, January 1970 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1970 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1970 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1970 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1970 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - University, A Princeton Quarterly (Summer, 1970) and Newspaper Clippings, June 1970 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Time Magazine (July 27, 1970) and Newspaper Clippings, July 1970 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1970 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - An Action Plan For 1990, September 1970 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Thomas Says He Hopes For Best On Oil Package, October 1970 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1970 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Bits of Oil Cheer, December 1970 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - The Alberta Gas Trunk Line Annual Report 1970, 20th Annual Progress Edition, Northwest Territories 1970 Centennial The Royal Tour, and Annual report of the Commissioner of the Northwest Territories (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1971 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1971 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1971 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1971 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1971 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Gas Arctic Systems and Proposed Icebreaker-Reinforced Tanker Convoy System for Transporting Oil, Gas, and Other Minerals from the Arctic, June 1971 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Gas Arctic Systems Flying Tour, August 1971 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1971 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Uniform Alcoholism and Intoxication Treatment Act and Newspaper Clippings, December 1971 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Explorers Guide Canada's Arctic, Alberta Canada Map, and Newspaper Clippings, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1972 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, March 1972 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1972 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, May 1972 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1972 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Thomas Questions Runaway Proposal, July 1972 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Legislator Holds Stand On Leasing, September 1972 (Box 10, Folder 17)
  - Bullheadedness, March 1973 (Box 10, Folder 18)
  - Exotic Game and Newspaper Clippings, September 1973 (Box 10, Folder 19)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1973 (Box 10, Folder 20)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 21)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1974 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1974 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1974 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1974 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1974 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Alaska by Prof. Maynard M. Miller, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - The Black-Gold Rush, January 1975 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1975 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1975 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1975 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1975 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - The Gas Pipeline, December 1975 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1976 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Should The North Slope Haul Road Eventually Be Open To Everyone As Part of The Alaskan Highway System?, December 1976 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, January 1977 (Box 11, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1977 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1977 (Box 11, Folder 18)
  - State of the State January 10, 1978 Before the Alaska State Legislature Juneau, Alaska by Jay S. Hammond, Governor of Alaska, January 1978 (Box 11, Folder 19)
  - Hickel Cites Threat To Private Ownership, March 1978 (Box 11, Folder 20)
  - Hickel - Kachemak, April 1978 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Hickel - Re Kachemak Turn-Around, May 1978 (Box 11, Folder 22)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1978 (Box 11, Folder 23)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1978 (Box 11, Folder 24)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1978 (Box 11, Folder 25)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1978 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1978 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1978 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, July 1979 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1979 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1979 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - The Environment, November 1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Newspaper Clippings, June 1980 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1981 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Alaska's land: a jigsaw puzzle, April 1981 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Newspaper Clippings, February 1982 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, April 1982 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Newspaper Clippings, September 1982 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1982 (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1982 (Box 12, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper Clippings, August 1984 (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Newspaper Clippings, October 1984 (Box 12, Folder 17)
  - Magazine Clippings and Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
- 3. Personal, 1956-2006; 34 folders
  Series contains newspaper clippings, correspondence, a biographical sketch of Lowell Thomas Jr., biographies, autobiographies, and a Lake Placid Calendar.
  - From Lowell Thomas, Jr. to John [plus Afghanistan photo and "Guidepost"], January 1956-May 23, 1960 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Newspaper Clippings, November 1957 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, December 1957 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - McCall's Magazine (April 1969) (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence from Lowell Thomas Jr. to Mr. Robert Atwood, Publisher, January 1974 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Biographical Sketch, December 1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence from Electra to Lowell Thomas Jr. and Newspaper Clippings, January 1975 (Box 13, Folder 7)